<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The asolda blog</title>
    <link>https://asolda.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on The asolda blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 15:13:03 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://asolda.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How hugo turned me into a blogger wannabe</title>
      <link>https://asolda.github.io/post/Welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 15:13:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://asolda.github.io/post/Welcome/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-this&#34;&gt;What is this?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to finally start a blog. This is just a welcome message (mostly realized to test hugo, Github Pages and a few themes).
In this blog I will talk about the project I work on in my free time; topics range from machine/deep learning to social network analysis, distributed computing and more.
Some projects are my own ideas, others are the result of me playing with coll stuff you find around the web.
This first article is about the technical details behind the blog itself, what technologies I&amp;rsquo;m using, how I&amp;rsquo;ve set up my workflow and how hugo convinced me to start this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;about-this-article&#34;&gt;About this article&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is supposed to be a technical blog, a safe shelter for computer scientists and alikes.
How I am developing this blog can be interesting and usefull for other people who want to share their projects and their knowledge.
The idea here is to give you an overview of how I am developing and updating the blog from a technical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, alongside &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt;, are the main reasons why I have finally decided to start this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hugo&lt;/strong&gt; is &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;a fast and modern static website engine&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. That is, a &lt;strong&gt;HUGE&lt;/strong&gt; help when you want to just write your thoughs, without worrying about themes, styles, and general web-development-related issues.
It is easy to install and configure (short tutorial is down the road), light, fast (gotta love &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/&#34;&gt;go&lt;/a&gt;), open source&amp;hellip; I could go on for miles.
There are downsides and negative aspects too, but the moment you realize what hugo is meant for you also realize that negative aspects turn into features; you will realize this in a few weeks of usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Github Pages&lt;/strong&gt; allows you to create and publish websites for your projects, as well as personal blogs or portfolios.
The code for you site is hosted directly from your GitHub repository. Just edit, push, and your changes are live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way hugo and Github Pages interact is mesmerizing; this instruments team up for a produtictivity boost comparable to the introductions of rounded wheels over squared ones.
Damn, you gotta love this things; and to bring you on board with me, let&amp;rsquo;s dive into a tutorial on how to setup this workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that I will assume that you already use git. In case you don&amp;rsquo;t, &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Getting-Started-Installing-Git&#34;&gt;here you are&lt;/a&gt; (and you&amp;rsquo;re a bad person).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;let-s-start-the-party&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start the party&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-0-install-and-configure-hugo&#34;&gt;Step 0: Install and configure hugo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You only need to follow this steps the first time you use hugo. Since it is written in go, it supports multiple platforms and comes in pre-built binaries available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spf13/hugo/releases&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A complete installation guide is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/installing/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re on a Mac, I advice you install &lt;a href=&#34;http://brew.sh/&#34;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; and just &lt;code&gt;brew install hugo&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-you-start&#34;&gt;Before you start&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t already done that, check that hugo is correctly configured by running&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo help
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo is the main command, used to build your Hugo site.

Hugo is a Fast and Flexible Static Site Generator
built with love by spf13 and friends in Go.

Complete documentation is available at http://gohugo.io/.

Usage:
  hugo [flags]
  hugo [command]
  ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It goes on for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1-create-your-first-hugo-project&#34;&gt;Step 1: Create your first hugo project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this short example we will create a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo has a large set of commands to manage your website. To create a new website move to a convenient location and run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo new site blog
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change directory to &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt; and you will see that hugo has created directories to store all the files required for your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;drwxr-xr-x  2 user   68 Nov 30 23:58 archetypes
-rw-r--r--  1 user   97 Dec  1 00:22 config.toml
drwxr-xr-x  3 user  102 Nov 30 23:59 content
drwxr-xr-x  2 user   68 Nov 30 23:58 data
drwxr-xr-x  2 user   68 Nov 30 23:58 layouts
drwxr-xr-x  2 user   68 Nov 30 23:58 static
drwxr-xr-x  6 user  204 Dec  1 00:20 themes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directory has 6 sub-directories and 1 file. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at each one of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;archetypes: You can create new content files in hugo using the &lt;code&gt;hugo new&lt;/code&gt; command.
When you run that command, it adds few configuration properties to the post like date and title.
Archetype allows you to define your own configuration properties that will be added to the post front matter whenever &lt;code&gt;hugo new&lt;/code&gt; command is used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;config.toml: Every website should have a configuration file at the root.
By default, the configuration file uses &lt;code&gt;TOML&lt;/code&gt; format but you can also use &lt;code&gt;YAML&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;JSON&lt;/code&gt; formats as well.
&lt;code&gt;TOML&lt;/code&gt; is minimal configuration file format that’s easy to read due to obvious semantics.
The configuration settings mentioned in the &lt;code&gt;config.toml&lt;/code&gt; are applied to the full site.
These configuration settings include &lt;code&gt;baseurl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; of the website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;content: This is where you will store content of the website.
Inside &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt;, you will create sub-directories for different sections.
Let’s suppose your website has three actions – blog, article, and tutorial then you will have three different directories for each of them inside the content directory.
The name of the section i.e. blog, article, or tutorial will be used by Hugo to apply a specific layout applicable to that section.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;data: This directory is used to store configuration files that can be used by Hugo when generating your website.
You can write these files in &lt;code&gt;YAML&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;JSON&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;TOML&lt;/code&gt; format.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;layouts: The content inside this directory is used to specify how your content will be converted into the static website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;static: This directory is used to store all the static content that your website will need like images, CSS, JavaScript or other static content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2-create-contents&#34;&gt;Step 2: Create contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s add a new post to our &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt;. We will use the &lt;code&gt;hugo new&lt;/code&gt; command to create a new post.
In our example, we want to create a welcome post to greet users visiting our blog.
Make sure you are inside the &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt; directory and type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo new post/welcome
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create a new directory &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt; inside the &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory, and a new file named &lt;code&gt;welcome.md&lt;/code&gt; inside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content of &lt;code&gt;welcome.md&lt;/code&gt; will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+++
draft = true
title = &amp;quot;welcome&amp;quot;
date = &amp;quot;2016-12-01T00:22:59+01:00&amp;quot;

+++
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content inside &lt;code&gt;+++&lt;/code&gt; is the TOML configuration for the post.
This configuration is called &lt;strong&gt;front matter&lt;/strong&gt;.
It enables you to define post configuration along with its content.
By default, each post will have the three configuration properties shown above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s add a short welcome message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+++
draft = true
title = &amp;quot;welcome&amp;quot;
date = &amp;quot;2016-12-01T00:22:59+01:00&amp;quot;

+++

Welcome to my blog!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3-serve-content&#34;&gt;Step 3: Serve content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo has an inbuilt server that can serve your website content so that you can preview it.
You can also use the inbuilt Hugo server in production.
Place yourself in the &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt; directory and run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo server
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The output will read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;0 of 1 draft rendered
0 future content
0 pages created
0 paginator pages created
0 tags created
0 categories created
in 9 ms
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can view your blog at &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313&#34;&gt;http://localhost:1313&lt;/a&gt;, go check it out&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s a blank page.
That&amp;rsquo;s because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the &lt;code&gt;hugo server&lt;/code&gt; command output, Hugo didn’t render the draft.
Hugo will only render drafts if you pass the &lt;code&gt;buildDrafts&lt;/code&gt; flag to the hugo server command.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have to specify a theme that Hugo can use to render the content.
We will do that in the next step.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To render drafts, run &lt;code&gt;hugo server --buildDrafts&lt;/code&gt; and head back to &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313&#34;&gt;http://localhost:1313&lt;/a&gt;.
Yet another wonderful blank page. We are missing the theme, remember that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4-add-theme&#34;&gt;Step 4: Add theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Themes provide the layout and templates that will be used by Hugo to render your website.
There are a lot of open-source themes available &lt;a href=&#34;https://themes.gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that you can use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to add a theme move to the &lt;code&gt;themes&lt;/code&gt; directory inside the root of your website and clone a theme for your website.
For our example, we will use the &lt;code&gt;bleak&lt;/code&gt; theme (the same I am using for my blog).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inside the themes directory&lt;/strong&gt; run &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/Zenithar/hugo-theme-bleak.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get back to the &lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt; directory (&lt;code&gt;cd ..&lt;/code&gt;) and run &lt;code&gt;hugo server --theme=hugo-theme-bleak --buildDrafts&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313&#34;&gt;http://localhost:1313&lt;/a&gt; and enjoy your freshly crafted blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s get back to code and try to understand how themes work, in order to customize and modify them.
A theme consist of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;theme.toml&lt;/strong&gt; is the theme configuration file that gives information about the theme like name and description of theme, author details, and theme license.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;images&lt;/strong&gt; directory contains four images, &lt;code&gt;screenshot.png&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tn.png&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;full_blog.png&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;full_post.png&lt;/code&gt;.
These images are examples of what the theme looks like;
as an example &lt;code&gt;screenshot.png&lt;/code&gt; is the image of the list view and &lt;code&gt;tn.png&lt;/code&gt; is the single post view.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;layouts&lt;/strong&gt; directory contains different views for different content types.
Every content type should have two files &lt;code&gt;single.html&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;list.html&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;single.html&lt;/code&gt; is used for rendering a single piece of content.
&lt;code&gt;list.html&lt;/code&gt; is used to view a list of content items.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;static&lt;/strong&gt; directory stores all the static assets used by the template.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously you can clone multiple themes and test theme using the &lt;code&gt;--theme&lt;/code&gt; argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-5-update-config-file&#34;&gt;Step 5: Update config file&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website uses the dummy values specified in &lt;code&gt;blog/config.toml&lt;/code&gt;.
Let’s update the configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;baseurl = &amp;quot;https://mywebsite.com&amp;quot;
title = &amp;quot;My blog&amp;quot;
languageCode = &amp;quot;en-us&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;optional-add-comments&#34;&gt;Optional: Add comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To integrate comments in your blog you can use &lt;strong&gt;Disqus&lt;/strong&gt;. Just open the &lt;code&gt;blog/config.toml&lt;/code&gt; file and add&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Params]
  disqusShortname = &amp;lt;your disqus shortname&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, commenting will be enabled in your blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-6-make-post-public&#34;&gt;Step 6: Make post public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our welcome post is still in &lt;code&gt;draft&lt;/code&gt; status.
To make a draft public, you can either run this command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo undraft content/post/welcome.md
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or manually change the draft status in the post to &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can start the server without the &lt;code&gt;buildDrafts&lt;/code&gt; argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo server --theme=hugo-theme-bleak
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-7-generate-website&#34;&gt;Step 7: Generate website&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To generate Hugo website source you can use to deploy your website on GitHub pages,
first edit &lt;code&gt;blog/config.toml&lt;/code&gt;, changing the baseurl line to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;baseurl = &amp;quot;https://username.github.io/&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo --theme=hugo-theme-bleak
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this command, a &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; folder will be created, containing teh generated source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-8-go-public&#34;&gt;Step 8: Go public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the github side of the thing, create a new &lt;strong&gt;empty&lt;/strong&gt; (no README) repo named &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now move to the &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; directory and add version control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git init
git remote add origin https://github.com/username/username.github.io.git
git add --all
git commit -m &amp;quot;First commit&amp;quot;
git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://username.github.io/&#34;&gt;https://username.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and enjoy your blog, now available online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anytime, you can regenerate the site with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo --theme=hugo-theme-bleak
cd public
git add --all
git commit -m &amp;quot;&amp;lt;some change message&amp;gt;&amp;quot;
git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>